<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                 "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="get-started">
    <title>Getting Started</title>

    <para>Learning a new framework is not always straight forward. In this section, we (the Spring DM team) 
    tried to provide, what we think is, an easy to follow guide for starting with Spring Dynamic Modules. 
    Of course, feel free to create your own learning 'path' as you see fit and, if possible, please report back
    any improvements to the documentation that can help others.</para>

    <section id="get-started:first-steps">
		<title>First Steps</title>
		
		<para>As explained in <xref linkend="why-Spring DM"/>, Spring DM provides integration between
		Spring framework and OSGi. Thus, it is important to become acquainted with both of these frameworks (libraries or
		environments depending on how you want to name them). Throughout the Spring DM documentation, each section provides
		links to resources relevant however, it is best to become familiar with these topics beforehand.</para>
		  
		<section id="get-started:first-steps:spring">
			<title>Knowing Spring</title>
			<para>Spring DM uses heavily Spring framework's <ulink url="http://static.springframework.org/spring/docs/2.5.x/reference/spring-core.html">core</ulink> functionalty, 
			such as the <ulink url="http://static.springframework.org/spring/docs/2.5.x/reference/beans.html">IoC</ulink> container,
			<ulink url="http://static.springframework.org/spring/docs/2.5.x/reference/resources.html">resource</ulink> abstract or
			<ulink url="http://static.springframework.org/spring/docs/2.5.x/reference/aop.html">AOP</ulink> infrastructure. While it is not important
			to know the Spring APIs, understanding the concepts behind them is. At a minimum, the idea behind IoC should be familiar.
			These being said, the more knowledge one has about the Spring, the faster she will pick Spring Dynamic Modules.
			Besides the very comprehensive (and sometimes disarming) documentation that explains in detail the Spring Framework,
			there are a lot of articles, blog entries and books on the matter - take a look at the Spring framework
			<ulink url="http://www.springsource.org/documentation">home page</ulink> for more information. In general, this should be the starting point for 
			OSGi (or Eclipse plugin) developers wanting to try Spring DM.</para>
		</section>
		<section id="get-started:first-steps:osgi">
			<title>Knowing OSGi</title>
			<para>Java developers, new to OSGi, can start by reading the OSGi Alliance <ulink url="http://www.osgi.org/About/HowOSGi">introduction</ulink>,
			the OSGi <ulink url="http://www.osgi.org/Specifications/HomePage">specifications</ulink> or one of the articles/blogs 
			available on the internet (such as the SpringSource <ulink url="http://blog.springsource.com/category/osgi/">blogs</ulink>).
			Additionally, the Spring DM home <ulink url="http://www.springframework.org/osgi">page</ulink> hosts various links to useful materials.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section id="get-started:first-steps:samples">
			<title>Trying Out The Samples</title>
			<para>Once one is familiar with the concepts behind Spring and OSGi, she can start reading the Spring DM reference documentation (this document) and
			take the Spring DM samples for a spin. The samples are available either in the .zip distribution or from the Spring DM repository.
			The samples are a convenient way to get started quickly with Spring DM as they show various features of Spring DM and help one get pass the 
			initial struggles with OSGi. However, they are not meant as the definitive guide in using OSGi rather, they aim to be a launching pad 
			for "newbies" trying out OSGi in Spring.
			</para>
			<para>The current distribution contains:</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Simple Service Sample</para>
					<para>A simple example that illustrates OSGi service publication and consumption through Spring DM. This is a good starting point
					for users learning the basics.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Weather Sample</para>
					<para>A demo that shows more advanced features of Spring DM and OSGi. The application creates a very simple weather information services 
					presenting some best practices in designing an application to take advantage of the modularity offered by OSGi.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Simple Web App Sample</para>
					<para>As the name implies, this is a simple web application, containing Servlets, JSPs and JSP tags, that runs inside OSGi through Spring DM.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Web Console Sample</para>
					<para>A more complicated sample that demos a Spring MVC annotation based, web application that runs inside OSGi through Spring DM, featuring 
					class path scanning and various Spring taglib. Additionally, the web application interacts with the OSGi environment through the web UI.</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist> 
			<para>Each project contains instructions regarding its content and startup procedure. Users are encouraged to experiment with the samples to get a better
			understanding of the technologies used.</para>
		</section>
	</section>
    
    <section id="get-started:help">
		<title>Need Help?</title>
		
		<para>If you encounter issues or you are just looking for an advice, feel free to use one of the links below:</para>
		
		<section id="get-started:help:community">
  		    <title>Community Support</title>
			<para>The Spring DM <ulink url="http://forum.springframework.org/forumdisplay.php?f=43">forum</ulink> is a message board for all Spring DM users to
			share information and help each other. Note that registration is needed <emphasis>only</emphasis> for posting.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section id="get-started:help:professional">
  		    <title>Professional Support</title>
			<para>Professional, from-the-source support, with guaranteed response time, is available from <ulink url="http://www.springsource.com">SpringSource</ulink>,
			the company behind Spring Dynamic Modules and Spring.  
			</para>
		</section>
    </section>
    
    <section id="get-started:up-to-date">
		<title>Following Development</title>
		
		<para>For information on the Spring DM source code repository, nightly builds and snapshot artifacts please see the Spring DM home 
		<ulink url="http://www.springsource.org/osgi">page</ulink>.   
		</para>
		<para>You can help make Spring DM best serve the needs of the Spring community by interacting with developers through the Spring Community 
		<ulink url="http://forum.springsource.org">forums</ulink>.</para>
		<para>If you encounter a bug or want to suggest an improvement, 
		please create a ticket on the Spring DM issue <ulink url="http://jira.springframework.org/">tracker</ulink>.</para>
		<para>To stay up to date with the latest news and announcements in the Spring eco system, subscribe to the 
		Spring Community <ulink url="http://www.springframework.org/">Portal</ulink>.</para>
	</section>
    
</chapter>