<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                 "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<appendix id="appendix-extensions">
    <title>Extensions</title>

	<sidebar>
	  <title>Spring DM and Spring annotations</title>
	  <para>This chapter describes the annotations present in Spring DM and how
	  to enable/disable them. Spring DM annotatations are separate from the <ulink url="http://static.springframework.org/spring/docs/2.5.x/reference/new-in-2.html#new-in-2-ioc-annotations">annotation</ulink> <ulink url="http://static.springframework.org/spring/docs/2.5.x/reference/new-in-2.html#new-in-2-ioc-component-scanning">support</ulink> in Spring
	  framework; enabling or disabling one does not interfere with the other.</para>
	</sidebar>
		
    <para>This appendix describes extensions to the core functionality that
    are shipped with the 1.0 distribution, but are not guaranteed to have
    backwards compatibility across point releases. We anticipate these
    features migrating into the core specification in future releases.</para>

    <section id="appendix-extensions:annotations">
      <title>Annotation-Based Injection</title>

      <para>The
      <literal>org.springframework.osgi.extensions.annotation</literal> bundle
      that ships with Spring Dynamic Modules provides early access to
      annotation-based support for injecting references to OSGi services. JDK
      1.5 or above is required to use this feature.</para>

      <para>Bean class (setter) methods may be annotated with
      <literal>org.springframework.osgi.extensions.annotation.ServiceReference</literal>.
      By default the property type of the annotated property is used to look
      up a service with a matching service interface in the OSGi service
      registry and inject the result. For example, given the
      configuration:</para>

      <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<bean id="annotationDriven" class="MyAnnotationDrivenBeanClass"/>
      ]]></programlisting>

      <para>and the class declaration:</para>

      <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[public class MyAnnotationDrivenBeanClass {

  @ServiceReference
  public void setMessageService(MessageService aService) { ... }

}]]></programlisting>

      <para>then a service lookup for services implementing the
      <interfacename>MessageService</interfacename> interface will be performed, and the
      best match (using the same algorithm as documented for the
      <literal>reference</literal> element) will be injected.</para>

      <para>The <classname>ServiceReference</classname> annotation class has a
      number of attributes that can be used to control the service lookup (for
      example, to specify a filter string) that mirror the options provided by
      the <literal>reference</literal> element. See the javadoc for more
      information.</para>
      
      <section id="appendix-extensions:annotations:enable">
		<title>Enabling/Disabling Annotation Processing</title>
		
		<para>By default, as Spring-OSGi is JDK 1.4 compatible, annotation injection is disabled. There are
		currently two ways for enabling it:</para>
		
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>through Spring DM extender (see <xref linkend="app-deploy:extender-configuration"/>).</para>
			  <para>This is an extender wide configuration which means all bundles started by the extender will have annotation injection applied to them.
			  </para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem><para>by specifying a dedicated bean post processor</para>
			<para>By specifying the Spring DM annotation extension processor, one
			can enable <emphasis>per-bundle</emphasis> annotation injection. To do that, add the following to your bundle configuration:</para>
			<programlisting><![CDATA[<!-- annotation processor -->
<bean class="org.springframework.osgi.extensions.annotation.ServiceReferenceInjectionBeanPostProcessor"/>]]></programlisting>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		
		<para>As a reminder, for the annotations to work, the containing bundle needs to import <literal>org.springframework.osgi.extensions.annotation</literal>
		package, which is available in the <literal>spring-osgi-annotation</literal> bundle.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
</appendix>
