<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<book xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <bookinfo>
    <title>Spring Dynamic Modules for <trademark>OSGi</trademark> Service Platforms</title>
    <subtitle>Known Issues</subtitle>
	<releaseinfo>&version;</releaseinfo>

    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Costin</firstname>
        <surname>Leau</surname>
		<affiliation>SpringSource</affiliation>        
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>Copies of this document may be made for your own use and for
      distribution to others, provided that you do not charge any fee for such
      copies and further provided that each copy contains this Copyright
      Notice, whether distributed in print or electronically.</para>
    </legalnotice>
  </bookinfo>

  <toc />

  <preface id="preface">
	<title>Preface</title>
	<para>
	  This document describes known issues (and possible work-arounds). Each issue mentions the section of the reference
	  documentation that explain the behaviour along with the associated
	  <ulink url="http://jira.springframework.org/browse/OSGI">JIRA</ulink> entry which
	  provides an estimate on when it will be solved.
	  As a rule, the next release Spring Dynamic Modules aims to solve most, if not all of them.
	</para>
  </preface>
  
  <chapter id="known-issues">
    <title>Known Issues</title>

	<para>As a side note, it worth pointing out that the issues below are not really bugs but rather improvements.</para>		

	<section id="OSGI-237">
      <title>Publishing prototypes as OSGi services</title>
      	<para>Due to the way OSGi platform deals with OSGi services (it caches the instance and returns it every time), prototypes are not fully supported.
      	Spring DM publishes a proxy that on each call, delegates back to the target application context for retrieving the instance. While with other beans
      	this works, in case of prototypes, this results in one-instance-per-invocation which is incorrect. Additional functionality needs to be added
      	to fully support prototypes even though, as pointed out, this involves a knowledge between Client/Server regarding the publication contract.</para>
      	<para>See <ulink url="http://jira.springframework.org/browse/OSGI-237">OSGI-237</ulink></para> 
	</section>	

  </chapter>
</book>
