      <partintro>
      <title>Document structure</title>

	  <para>This part of the reference documentation explains the core functionality
	  offered by Spring Dynamic Modules.</para>
      
      <para><xref linkend="bnd-app-ctx"/> describes the relationship between an OSGi Bundle and a 
      Spring Application Context,
      and introduces the Spring Extender Bundle support for instantiating
      application contexts automatically.</para>

      <para><xref linkend="app-deploy"/> describes how to deploy the Spring Framework jar files in
      an OSGi environment, and how to reference external APIs from your
      application bundles should you need to do so. This chapter also explains
      some of the issues to be aware of when using existing enterprise
      libraries not designed for OSGi in an OSGi environment.</para>

      <para><xref linkend="service-registry"/> describes how to export Spring
      beans as services in the OSGi service registry, and how to inject
      references to OSGi services into beans. This chapter also defines how
      the dynamic life-cycle of OSGi services and bundles is supported.</para>

      <para><xref linkend="bundles"/> describes how to declare a bean
      that represents an OSGi bundle, including support for installing new
      bundles into the OSGi platform.</para>

      <para><xref linkend="web"/> explains how to run web applications inside
      an OSGi environment using Spring DM.</para>
      
      <para><xref linkend="compendium"/> describes the support provided
      for the <ulink url="http://www2.osgi.org/Release4/Download">OSGi
      Compendium Services</ulink>, specifically the Configuration Admin
      service.</para>
      
      <para><xref linkend="testing"/> explains the
      integration testing support provided by Spring Dynamic Modules. This
      support enables you to write simple JUnit integration tests that can
      start up an OSGi environment, install the bundles needed for the
      integration test, execute the test case(s) inside of OSGi, and return
      the results to the runner. This makes it easy to integrate OSGi
      integration testing into any environment that can work with
      JUnit.</para>

      </partintro>